[Informally, before the puja speech to some persons]
Shri Adi Shakti Puja, Cheltenham, Inglaterra, 01.08.1982
Shri Mataji: Just help him, one person can’t do it, somebody else.
Apenas o ajudem, uma só pessoa não pode fazer isso, alguma outra pessoa,
Marcus, Nick, anyone, just help him out,
Marcus, Nick, qualquer um, apenas o ajudem, isso é demais para uma só pessoa,
it’s too much for one person, just help him, please.
apenas o ajudem, por favor.
What’s there?
O que há?
Alan, go and tell Bai to bring My handkerchief from My...
Alan, vá e diga a Bai para trazer Meu lenço de minha...
I’ve got My pur- No, no, it’s all right, it’s here,
Eu trouxe Minha bolsa - não, não, está tudo bem, ele está aqui,
with My purse, have you brought it? Yes, it’s here. Don’t worry, don’t worry!
em Minha bolsa, você a trouxe? Sim, está aqui. Não se preocupe, não se preocupe.
Man: Here’s Your purse, Mother.
Aqui está sua bolsa, Mãe.
Shri Mataji: Have the Americans come, those who have done the Puja, have they come?
Os americanos vieram? Aqueles que fizeram o Puja, eles vieram?
Sahaja yogi: Yes, Mother. Shri Mataji: Are they here? Man: Yes.
- Sim, Mãe. - Eles estão aqui?
Shri Mataji: Oh, they are here. Then it’s all right.
Ah, eles estão aqui. Então está tudo bem.
And, in these new centers,
E, nesses novos centros,
have you started with Puja anywhere? Sahaja Yogini: Yes, Mother.
vocês começaram com Puja em algum lugar?
Shri Mataji: No, yours is all right, I’m asking about England.
Não, o de vocês está bem, estou perguntando sobre a Inglaterra.
Warren: Any centres in Britain? Where there are new people.
Algum centro na Grã-Bretanha? Onde há pessoas novas.
Shri Mataji: Cheltenham, for example. Where is Alan? Ask him.
Cheltenham, por exemplo. Onde está Alan? Perguntem a ele.
Warren: He’s just gone out for a moment. Any centers in Britain,
Ele acabou de sair por um momento. De algum centro na Grã-Bretanha,
any new people here, right now?
há alguma pessoa nova aqui, agora?
Shri Mataji: If do you have introduced them to puja I don’t mind,
Se vocês os introduziram ao Puja, não Me importo,
but if they have never been introduced to puja, then you have to be careful.
mas se nunca foi introduzido o Puja a eles, então vocês devem ter cuidado.
From their good point of view.
A partir do bom ponto de vista deles.
I’m sorry I had to say this,
Eu lamento ter de dizer isso,
because yesterday the load was too much, you know I couldn’t speak even,
porque ontem a carga foi muita, Eu não conseguia nem mesmo falar,
and lifting the Kundalini was like raising hundred donkeys on your head,
e levantar a Kundalini era como levantar cem burros na sua cabeça,
it was too much.
aquilo foi demasiado.
And all these half-baked people are such that they are like dog-in-the-manger,
E todas essas pessoas mal desenvolvidas são de tal forma...
they won’t have it and they won’t allow others to have it.
elas não o terão e não permitirão que outros o tenham.
They’ll argue before the program, before the meeting starts,
Elas discutirão antes do programa, antes do encontro começar,
before the puja starts, specially.
antes do puja começar, especialmente.
Because they don’t want you to enjoy the fruits of the puja;
Porque elas não querem que vocês desfrutem os frutos do puja,
they’ll spoil your attention,
elas estragarão a atenção de vocês,
they’ll argue, discuss. [Aside: “Please sit down.”]
elas argumentarão, discutirão. Por favor, sente-se.
What is there to argue in Sahaj Yoga? You have to take, that’s the point is,
O que há para discutir na Sahaja Yoga? Você tem de aceitar, esse é o ponto,
you have to take, there’s nothing to argue.
você tem de aceitar, não há nada para discutir.
How much you take is the point.
O quanto você aceita é o ponto.
And the worst part is that they don’t want to grow and they want to pull you down.
E a pior parte é que elas não querem crescer e querem rebaixá-los.
So, unless and until they are introduced to the idea of puja beforehand -
Portanto, a menos e até que lhes seja introduzida de antemão a ideia de puja,
then they start understanding the worth of puja, otherwise they do not,
então elas começam a entender o valor do puja, caso contrário elas não entendem,
how will they understand? You see, it’s beyond them.
como elas entenderão? Isso está além delas.
So, you should not make them attend any puja, minimum,
Então, vocês não devem fazê-las participar de nenhum puja, no mínimo,
and also seminars I would say. Because seminars are meant for people
e também de seminários, Eu diria, porque os seminários são para pessoas…
who are intensively in Sahaj Yoga, to intensify their awareness.
que estão intensamente na Sahaja Yoga, para intensificar a consciência delas.
Not for people who are half-baked, who are Doubting Thomases,
Não para as pessoas que são mal desenvolvidas, que são céticas,
all this kind of people are absolutely useless,
todos esses tipos de pessoas são totalmente inúteis,
you should never bring them to a seminar.
vocês nunca devem trazê-las para um seminário.
Whether it’s your son, father, brother, mother, sister, husband, wife,
Quer seja seu filho, pai, irmão, mãe, irmã, marido, esposa, de maneira nenhuma.
fully awakened Sahaja Yogi,
um Sahaja Yogi totalmente desperto,
because seminars are meant for very intensive work-out.
porque os seminários são destinados a trabalhos muito intensos.
And what I find, always these people will argue with Me,
E o que Eu percebo é que essas pessoas sempre discutirão Comigo,
they are the first to question, they have something to say
elas são as primeiras a questionar, elas têm algo a dizer,
they are the ones. Sahaja Yogis are keeping quiet and receiving it.
elas são as que fazem isso. Os Sahaja Yogis ficam em silêncio e recebendo isso.
I don’t mind even that, but what happens in the seminar, you have to receive more.
Eu não Me importo nem mesmo com isso, mas o que acontece no seminário...
And they do not receive, their attention is outside, they are disturbing everyone.
E elas não recebem, a atenção delas está no externo, ficam perturbando todo mundo.
So, seminars are even, in a way, more important than an ashram,
Portanto, os seminários são até mesmo, de certa forma,
because in ashram there’s no other problem but to fight them out.
porque no ashram, não há nenhum outro problema, exceto lutar contra eles.
But here, in a new place we go, we have to fight out all surroundings,
Mas aqui, em um novo lugar que vamos, nós temos de lutar contra todo o ambiente,
the place itself has to be cleansed, everything has to be done.
o lugar em si tem de ser limpo, tudo tem de ser feito.
On top of that you have these horrible people around you,
Além disso, você tem essas pessoas horríveis ao seu redor,
whom you have to convince. If they are not convinced, why are they here?
que você tem de convencer. Se elas não estão convencidas, por que elas estão aqui?
Why did they spend so much money to come down?
Por que elas gastaram tanto dinheiro para vir?
Be sure, they have come here to disturb us. I’m sorry we had to do that way.
Tenham certeza, elas vieram aqui para nos perturbar.
I wish people could be simple, straightforward,
Eu gostaria que as pessoas pudessem ser simples, diretas,
uncomplicated, and sensitive, but they are not.
descomplicadas e sensíveis, mas elas não são.
They are not sensitive people. They don’t understand what are they up to.
Elas não são pessoas sensíveis, não entendem do que são capazes.
By that they destroy themselves, no doubt, but they destroy part of you also,
Através disso, elas se destroem, sem dúvida, mas destroem parte de vocês também,
and also trouble Me. Yesterday it was too heavy, you know that.
e também Me perturbam. Ontem estava muito pesado, vocês sabem disso.
Such a deep subject and it was too heavy for Me.
Um assunto tão profundo e foi tão pesado para Mim.
If they say they feel bad, all right, tell them: “We are sorry, we can’t help you.”
Se eles disserem que se sentem mal, tudo bem, diga-lhes:
See, there are certain points where we have to have our freedom
Há certos pontos em que temos de ter nossa liberdade…
to allow those who can come in. That’s the point where we close the door.
para permitir aqueles que podem entrar. Esse é o ponto em que fechamos a porta.
And there’s nothing wrong in it, because you have to equip more to pull them out.
E não há nada de errado nisso, porque você tem de se equipar mais para retirá-los.
It has been always our practice, since long, there’s nothing new about it,
Isso sempre foi nossa prática, desde muito tempo, não há nada de novo nisso,
everyone knows, not only in England, or any other place, even in India:
todos sabem, não só na Inglaterra ou em qualquer outro lugar, mesmo na Índia,
we never allowed anybody to come for the Puja who was not a realized soul,
nunca permitimos que alguém venha para o Puja que não seja uma alma realizada…
and who was not a Sahaja Yogi, from the very beginning.
e que não seja um Sahaja Yogi, desde o início.
Wherever we tried that, we found it was very difficult.
Onde quer que tentamos isso, nós descobrimos que era muito difícil.
So I hope there’s nobody sitting here with a doubting mind.
Então Eu espero que não haja ninguém sentado aqui com uma mente incrédula.
If somebody’s there he should with all sincerity leave the hall
Se há alguém, ele deve com toda sinceridade deixar o auditório…
and leave us alone, for the ascent.
e nos deixar em paz para a ascensão.
Anybody who has doubts should be kind and generous about it.
Qualquer um que tenha dúvidas deve ser gentil e generoso em relação a isso.
It’s a very serious work we are doing. It’s not of making money
É um trabalho muito sério que estamos fazendo. Não é para ganhar dinheiro…
or of throwing an enterprise or building a house or something like that.
ou para lançar um empreendimento ou construir uma casa ou algo assim.
It’s not even just making creations of worlds,
Não é nem mesmo apenas fazer criações de mundos,
it’s much more than that, it’s a very serious work we are doing
é muito mais que isso, é um trabalho muito sério que estamos fazendo…
and we don’t want anybody to cut our attention.
e não queremos que ninguém corte nossa atenção.
Even some of the Sahaja Yogis I know, are half-baked.
Mesmo alguns dos Sahaja Yogis, Eu sei, são mal desenvolvidos.
They must be corrected, all right, doesn’t matter, but they have been exposed to pujas,
Eles devem ser corrigidos, tudo bem, não importa, mas eles têm sido expostos a pujas,
so it will do them good, not bad.
então isso lhes fará bem, não mal.
But some people are just anti-God, and they have allergies for God.
Mas algumas pessoas são apenas anti-Deus e têm alergia a Deus.
Any work you’d start doing in the name of God, they are so allergic, they react.
Qualquer trabalho que você comece a fazer em nome de Deus,
These are anti-God allergies,
Essas são alergias anti-Deus…
and they express themselves by different, funny methods.
e elas se expressam por métodos diferentes, estranhos.
Now, all the Sahaja Yogis must know this, then you will not go too far with them.
Agora, todos os Sahaja Yogis devem saber disso,
You will - you should discover this in anyone this allergy existing.
Vocês devem descobrir em qualquer pessoa se existe essa alergia.
You should say: “Sorry, we have nothing to do with you”.
Vocês devem dizer: "Desculpe, não temos nada a ver com você".
So that is for the people who have to have the privilege of this worship.
Então isso é para as pessoas que têm de ter o privilégio dessa veneração.
Today is specially a great privilege
Hoje é especialmente um grande privilégio,
because it was not so planned,
porque não foi tão planejado, mas deu certo,
Yesterday we did lots of cleansing. Now, today tell your mind to rest for a while.
Ontem nós fizemos muita limpeza. Agora, hoje digam à sua mente...
Tell your thoughts to stop for a while, and receive, receive more of it.
Digam aos seus pensamentos para pararem por um tempo e recebam, recebam mais.
Everybody has benefited by this reception but you have to receive more.
Todo mundo se beneficiou ao receber, mas vocês têm de receber mais.
There’s a capacity within you to receive.
Há uma capacidade dentro de vocês para receber.
Puja, as I have told you many-a-times, is not for My benefit, by any chance,
O Puja, como Eu disse muitas vezes, não é para Meu benefício, de forma alguma,
take it from Me. I’m much better off without it.
acreditem em Mim. Eu estou muito melhor sem ele,
Because when the enthusiastic deities start emitting vibrations
porque quando as Divindades entusiasmadas começam a emitir vibrações…
with your asking - because you are saints, you see, just they are over-enthusiastic.
com o seu pedido - porque vocês são santos, Elas são excessivamente entusiasmadas.
And they are sitting there, busy-bodies, you know,
E as Divindades estão sentadas lá, "bisbilhoteiras",
they are sitting quietly waiting for a chance, you see, to emit vibrations,
estão sentadas em silêncio esperando por uma chance para emitir vibrações,
to save you, you see they want to just rush.
para salvá-los, as Divindades querem apenas se apressar.
They emit so much that they lose – “Just wait, just wait”.
Elas emitem tanto que desperdiçam: "Apenas aguardem, apenas aguardem".
They want to save you, they want to give you, they’re so anxious,
As Divindades querem salvá-los, querem lhes dar, estão tão ansiosas,
in their anxiety you see - I like it, to see the way they are anxious.
na ansiedade Delas, Eu gosto disso, ver o jeito que estão ansiosas.
But you don’t suck it, and I have a problem there.
Mas vocês não absorvem isso e Eu tenho um problema.
Once they have given they don’t want to take it back.
Uma vez que Elas deram, Elas não querem pegar de volta. Vocês não absorvem,
Is directed towards you and you don’t take it; so where does it go?
É direcionado para vocês e vocês não recebem, então para onde vai?
It hangs into My tissues, it pains Me.
Cai em Meus tecidos, causa-Me dor.
So, sucking should be more. Sucking should be more.
Então, a absorção deve ser maior, a absorção deve ser maior.
And just before the Puja you should say: “Mother, make me such
E logo antes do Puja, vocês devem dizer: "Mãe, torna-me de tal forma..."
that I suck more of the Divine”.
"que eu absorva mais do Divino".
Just pray that, with sincerity from your heart, just say that.
Apenas orem, com sinceridade, de coração, apenas digam isso.
There’s another beautiful gesture I have seen, in Uzbekistan, it’s very good.
Há outro belo gesto que Eu vi no Uzbequistão, é muito bom.
They put both the hands on their heart like this, and just press it,
Eles colocam as duas mãos no coração assim e apenas o pressionam,
bending their head, asking. See, it creates a vacuum.
inclinando a cabeça deles, pedindo. Isso cria um vácuo.
That’s how they bow.
É desse modo que eles se curvam.
It’s beautiful!
É lindo!
That’s very nice today.
Isto está muito bom hoje.
So, let the children come here.
Então, deixem as crianças virem aqui.
[Translation: “Come, sister has come, Sister has come”].
Venha, a irmã veio, a irmã veio.
Now, sit there, all of you sit down, all right? Sit down now, sit down, sit down.
Agora, sentem-se aí, todos vocês se sentem, tudo bem? Sentem-se agora, sentem-se.
Now, come along, Matthews is also coming, sit down there,
Agora, venham, Matthews também está vindo, sentem-se aí,
sit down, come along, let’s see, sit down. Now all the children are very sweet,
sentem-se, venham, vamos ver, sentem-se. Agora, todas as crianças são muito doces…
and are going to sit down. Come along, sit down, sit down, nicely.
e irão se sentar. Venham, sentem-se, sentem-se, tranquilamente.
[Translation: “Where is sister? Where is sister?”
Onde está a irmã? Onde está a irmã?
Younger granddaughter: Upstairs. Shri Mataji: Upstairs! Not yet come?]
- No andar de cima. - Lá em cima! Ainda não veio?
All right, now, you should give Me the flowers now,
Tudo bem, agora, vocês devem Me dar as flores agora,
so would be better for you to have vibrations, thank you.
então será melhor para vocês receberem vibrações, obrigada.
Thank you very much, thank you very much. Poor Rishi has none.
Muito obrigada, muito obrigada. Pobre Rishi não tem nenhuma.
Now, you give Me these, to Me, give Me now. Give Me. Give Me, to Mother.
Agora, dê-Me isto, para Mim, dê-Me agora. Dê-Me. Dê-Me, para a Mãe.
All right, give that also. Child [indistinctly]: But you have the one.
Tudo bem, dê isso também. Mas você tem um.
Shri Mataji: Also give. So thank you,
Dê também. Então obrigada,
thank you, thank you very much.
Obrigada. Muito obrigada.
[She hands the flowers to a lady aside: “All right, just take this”]
Tudo bem, é só pegar isto.
All right, so now what should we do, Pujari is this.
Tudo bem, então agora o que devemos fazer? O Pujari está aqui.
Just put a tikka to him. Put to everyone, not to the Pujari.
Basta colocar um tikka para ele. Coloque para todos, não para o Pujari.
Pujari: Got it.
Entendi.
Shri Mataji: All right. All right. That’s kajal? No, don’t put kajal.
Tudo bem. Tudo bem. Isto é kajal? Não, não coloque kajal.
He’ll be like Bhairava!
Ele ficará como Bhairava.
Good. May God bless you.
Bom. Que Deus os abençoe.
All right. Now, the children should sit like this, all right?
Tudo bem. Agora, as crianças devem sentar-se assim, tudo bem?
On the side, for Ganesha Puja, like this, straight.
Nos lados, para o Ganesha Puja, assim, eretas.
So everybody can take photograph also,
Assim todos podem tirar fotos também, sentem-se assim, tudo bem?
Oh, now sit here. Sit, sit down, all right.
Agora sentem-se aqui. Sentem-se, sentem-se, tudo bem.
Good, it’s very good. But you have to take out shoes!
Bom, está muito bom. Mas você tem de tirar os sapatos.
See, cannot have shoes here, take out shoes.
Veja, não pode ter sapatos aqui, tire os sapatos.
Take out shoes, everybody’s taken out shoes, take out, take out -
Tire os sapatos, todos tiraram os sapatos, tire, tire,
take out shoes. Yeah.
tire os sapatos. Sim.
So come along.
Então venha.
Sit like this, on the sides.
Sente-se assim, nas laterais.
[A lato: (Hindi) Shuddhi mein Ganesha Puja?] Pujari (in hindi): Ha, Shri Ganesha Puja.
- Shuddhi mein Ganesha Puja? - Sim, Shri Ganesha Puja.
Pujari: To begin with, we will do first the invocation of the puja,
Antes de tudo, faremos primeiro a invocação do puja,
then the puja to Lord Ganesha.
depois o puja para o Senhor Ganesha.
And this would be followed by the puja to the Adi Shakti, Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi.
E será seguido pelo puja à Adi Shakti Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi.
In the Devi Bhagavat Purana it is written that the puja to the Adi Shakti
No Devi Bhagavat Purana está escrito que o puja à Adi Shakti…
is the greatest puja that can be done by any being.
é o maior puja que pode ser feito por qualquer ser.
Shri Mataji: That’s why you are privileged.
É por isso que vocês são privilegiados.
Pujari: Even the Gods don’t do it. Shri Mataji: None of them.
- Nem os Deuses fazem isso. - Nenhum Deles.
They just touch My feet.
Eles apenas tocam Meus Pés.
None of them did Puja to Me. Believe Me.
Nenhum Deles fez Puja para Mim. Acreditem em Mim.
[Softly, to a little girl - ed] Very good. All right, sit down.
Muito bom. Tudo bem, sente-se.
Gli yogi: Om Twameva Sakshat, Shri Ganesha Sakshat,
Om Twameva Sakshat, Shri Ganesha Sakshat,
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat,
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat,
Shri Bhagavati Sakshat, Shri Mataji,
Shri Bhagavati Sakshat, Shri Mataji,
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Mataji: One person should say, then you can repeat, that’s better.
Uma pessoa deveria recitar, depois vocês podem repetir, é melhor.
What about Aradhna, where is she? She has not come? Child: She is upstairs.
- E Aradhna, onde ela está? Ela não veio? - Ela está lá em cima.
Pujari: We’ll start again. First Lord Ganesha,
Vamos começar de novo. Primeiro Senhor Ganesha,
then Mahalakshmi, Mahasaraswati, Mahakali.
depois Mahalakshmi, Mahasaraswati, Mahakali.
Then Lord Kalki and then Lord Kalki and Sahastrara Swamini.
Depois Senhor Kalki e depois Senhor Kalki e Sahastrara Swamini.
Yogi: Three times Shri Ganesha? Pujari: Hm?
- Três vezes Shri Ganesha? - Hã?
Yogi: How many times the Ganesha mantra? Pujari: Each once, I mean.
- Quantas vezes o mantra Ganesha? - Uma vez, quero dizer.
Gli yogi: Om Twameva Sakshat, Shri Ganesha Sakshat,
Om Twameva Sakshat, Shri Ganesha Sakshat,
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat,
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat,
Shri Bhagavati Sakshat, Shri Mataji,
Shri Bhagavati Sakshat, Shri Mataji,
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Om Twameva Sakshat Shri Mahalakshmi,
Om Twameva Sakshat Shri Mahalakshmi,
Mahasaraswati, Mahakali Trigunatmika,
Mahasaraswati, Mahakali Trigunatmika,
Kundalini Sakshat, Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat,
Kundalini Sakshat, Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat,
Shri Bhagavati Sakshat, Shri Mataji,
Shri Bhagavati Sakshat, Shri Mataji,
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Om Twameva Sakshat Shri Kalki Sakshat,
Om Twameva Sakshat Shri Kalki Sakshat,
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat,
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat,
Shri Bhagavati Sakshat, Shri Mataji,
Shri Bhagavati Sakshat, Shri Mataji,
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Om Twameva Sakshat Shri Kalki Sakshat,
Om Twameva Sakshat Shri Kalki Sakshat,
Shri Sahastrara Swamini Moksha Pradayini Mataji,
Shri Sahastrara Swamini Moksha Pradayini Mataji,
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Pujari: Now the names of Lord Vishnu. Om Shri Keshavaya Namah,
Agora os nomes do Senhor Vishnu. Om Shri Keshavaya Namah,
Om Shri Narayanaya Namah, Om Shri Madhavaya Namah,
Om Shri Narayanaya Namah, Om Shri Madhavaya Namah,
Om Shri Govindaya Namah, Om Shri Vishnuve Namah,
Om Shri Govindaya Namah, Om Shri Vishnuve Namah,
Om (Shri) Madhusudanaya Namah, Om Shri Trivikramaya Namah,
Om (Shri) Madhusudanaya Namah, Om Shri Trivikramaya Namah,
Om Shri Vamanaya Namah, Om Shri Shridharaya Namah,
Om Shri Vamanaya Namah, Om Shri Shridharaya Namah,
Om Shri Hrishikeshaya Namah, Om Shri Sankarshanaya Namah,
Om Shri Hrishikeshaya Namah, Om Shri Sankarshanaya Namah,
Om Shri Vasudevaya Namah, Om Shri Pradyumnaya Namah,
Om Shri Vasudevaya Namah, Om Shri Pradyumnaya Namah,
Om Shri Aniruddhaya Namah, Om Shri Purushottamaya Namah,
Om Shri Aniruddhaya Namah, Om Shri Purushottamaya Namah,
Om Shri Aghokshajaya Namah, Om Shri Narasimhaya Namah,
Om Shri Aghokshajaya Namah, Om Shri Narasimhaya Namah,
Om Shri Achyutaya Namah, Om Shri Janardanaya Namah,
Om Shri Achyutaya Namah, Om Shri Janardanaya Namah,
Om Shri Padmanabhaya Namah, Om Shri Damodaraya Namah,
Om Shri Padmanabhaya Namah, Om Shri Damodaraya Namah,
Om Shri Upendraya Namah, Om Shri Haraye Namah,
Om Shri Upendraya Namah, Om Shri Haraye Namah,
Om Shri Krishnaye Namah.
Om Shri Krishnaye Namah.
Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Mataji: Why these twenty-one names are taken before every puja,
Por que esses 21 nomes são recitados antes de cada puja,
even before the today renovation of it?
antes mesmo da renovação de hoje disso?
First you have to worship Shri Ganesha.
Primeiro você tem de venerar Shri Ganesha.
But even before worshipping why these names are taken,
Mas mesmo antes de venerar, por que esses nomes são recitados?
is important to understand, everything has a why.
É importante entender, tudo tem um porquê.
Because these are the twenty-one channels within your Sushumna,
Porque estes são os 21 canais dentro de seu Sushumna,
twenty-one channels, we should say, in this
21 canais, nós devemos dizer, nestes…
complete Ida, Pingala and Sushumna Nadi.
Ida, Pingala e Sushumna Nadi completos.
So to raise you,
Então, para elevar vocês,
absolutely to give you the ascent, twenty- one channels in Ida, Pingala, Sushumna.
absolutamente, para lhes dar a ascensão, 21 canais no Ida, Pingala, Sushumna.
So one would say seven channels in the Sushumna Nadi.
então podemos dizer sete canais no Sushumna Nadi.
But these seven channels are divided multiplied by seven into three.
Mas esses sete canais são multiplicados por sete vezes três.
So every channel has got twenty-one (inner? Unclear) channels.
Assim, cada canal tem 21 canais internos.
So Sushumna Nadi has got also twenty-one channels.
Então o Sushumna Nadi também tem 21 canais.
Left-hand side Nadis are as you know that –
Os Nadis do canal esquerdo são, como vocês sabem,
perhaps you know, I don’t know if you know the names or not.
talvez vocês saibam, Eu não sei se vocês sabem os nomes ou não.
And the right hand side also, like Gayatri,
E o canal direito também, como Gayatri,
Parvati and all these are on the righ hand side.
Parvati e todos estes estão do canal direito.
And the left ones are called as Chamundi,
E os do canal esquerdo são chamados de Chamundi,
and all these left-sided things, there are seven of them.
e todas essas coisas do canal esquerdo, há sete delas.
Now, the central path has got twenty-one channels and has got twenty-one powers.
Agora, o canal central tem 21 canais e tem 21 poderes.
And their deities are named
E suas Divindades são nomeadas…
according to the twenty-one aspects of Shri Vishnu.
de acordo com os 21 aspectos de Shri Vishnu.
And that’s why these twenty-one aspects are first said,
E é por isso que esses 21 aspectos são recitados primeiro,
so that within you all these twenty-one channels are awakened.
de modo que, dentro de vocês, todos esses 21 canais sejam despertados.
Within you, first of all.
Dentro de vocês, antes de tudo.
Puja is a double thing, that a cup has to be made
O Puja é uma coisa dupla, em que uma taça tem de ser feita...
and then this source has to be opened out.
e depois essa fonte tem de ser aberta.
So you are the cup. The Sushumna is the channel you have by which you suck in.
Então vocês são a taça.
So to open the Sushumna these twenty-one names are said.
Então, para abrir o Sushumna, esses 21 nomes são recitados.
Now, why first Shri Ganesha?
Agora, por que primeiro Shri Ganesha?
Because Shri Ganesha is the beginning of the desire. And the end of the desire.
Porque Shri Ganesha é o começo do desejo e o fim do desejo.
You start with Ganesha and end up with Ganesha.
Vocês começam com Ganesha e terminam com Ganesha.
And that’s why Shri Ganesha is worshipped.
E é por isso que Shri Ganesha é venerado. É o contrário agora, é a fonte.
When you direct your attention to the source you worship it,
Quando vocês dirigem sua atenção para a fonte, você veneram,
and when you want to incite or open out your own being, then you chant it.
e quando vocês querem incitar ou abrir seu próprio ser, então vocês recitam.
This is the difference between worship and a mantra.
Essa é a diferença entre veneração e um mantra.
If you just say mantra, you open yourself up.
Se vocês simplesmente recitarem o mantra, vocês se abrem.
But when you worship and chant, then you tap the source.
Mas quando vocês veneram e recitam, então vocês destampam a fonte.
I don’t know if I’ve said this before or not.
Eu não sei se Eu disse isso antes ou não.
Yogi: No, no, no. Shri Mataji: No? All right.
- Não, não, não. - Não? Tudo bem.
That’s how you understand the puja part.
É desse modo que vocês entendem a parte do puja.
Now, those who are newcomers, their cup is completely useless.
Agora, aqueles que são novatos, a taça deles é completamente inútil.
And when you excite the deities, they get busy opening their cups,
E quando vocês estimulam as Divindades, Elas ficam ocupadas abrindo as taças Delas,
everybody’s cups also. So it’s a double work.
as taças de todos também. Então é um trabalho duplo.
But if your cup is ready, it’s very easy to fill in.
Mas se sua taça estiver pronta, é muito fácil enchê-la.
So now these twenty-one names I think you should take again
Então agora, esses 21 nomes, Eu acho que vocês deveriam recitar de novo…
with the understanding, is better. All right.
com o entendimento, é melhor. Tudo bem.
Pujari: Om Shri Keshavaya Namah, Om Shri Narayanaya Namah,
Om Shri Keshavaya Namah, Om Shri Narayanaya Namah,
Om Shri Madhavaya Namah, Om Shri Govindaya Namah,
Om Shri Madhavaya Namah, Om Shri Govindaya Namah,
Om Shri Vishnuve Namah, Om (Shri) Madhusudanaya Namah,
Om Shri Vishnuve Namah, Om (Shri) Madhusudanaya Namah,
Om Shri Trivikramaya Namah, Om Shri Vamanaya Namah,
Om Shri Trivikramaya Namah, Om Shri Vamanaya Namah,
Om Shri Shridharaya Namah, Om Shri Hrishikeshaya Namah,
Om Shri Shridharaya Namah, Om Shri Hrishikeshaya Namah,
Om Shri Sankarshanaya Namah, Om Shri Vasudevaya Namah,
Om Shri Sankarshanaya Namah, Om Shri Vasudevaya Namah,
Om Shri Pradyumnaya Namah, Om Shri Aniruddhaya Namah,
Om Shri Pradyumnaya Namah, Om Shri Aniruddhaya Namah,
Om Shri Purushottamaya Namah, Om Shri Aghokshajaya Namah,
Om Shri Purushottamaya Namah, Om Shri Aghokshajaya Namah,
Om Shri Narasimhaya Namah, Om Shri Achyutaya Namah,
Om Shri Narasimhaya Namah, Om Shri Achyutaya Namah,
Om Shri Janardanaya Namah, Om Shri Padmanabhaya Namah,
Om Shri Janardanaya Namah, Om Shri Padmanabhaya Namah,
Om Shri Damodaraya Namah, Om Shri Upendraya Namah,
Om Shri Damodaraya Namah, Om Shri Upendraya Namah,
Om Shri Haraye Namah, Om Shri Krishnaye Namah.
Om Shri Haraye Namah, Om Shri Krishnaye Namah.
Pujari e gli yogi: Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Mataji: Now.
Agora.
Pujari: Now we have the mantra for pranayama.
Agora nós temos o mantra para pranayama.
Shri Mataji: This is the Gayatri, the right side.
Este é o Gayatri, o canal direito.
Is the right side, and these are all the seven centers on physical level.
É o canal direito e estes são todos os sete centros no nível físico.
Pujari: Pranayama. Shri Mataji: Pranayama is the same thing. Is for –
- Pranayama. - Pranayama é a mesma coisa. É para -
Prana is right side. It’s physical side. You are opening the right side.
Prana é o canal direito. É o lado físico. Vocês estão abrindo o canal direito.
You see, this Gayatri mantra you say. Bhur Bhuva Swaha and all these things.
Este mantra Gayatri, recitem: Bhur Bhuva Swaha e todas essas coisas.
Now, Bhu is Pruthvi, Bhuva is Antariksha,
Agora, Bhu é Pruthvi, Bhuva é Antariksha.
you see, like that, it’s all the centers [Pujari: “Swaha”],
Desse jeito, são todos os centros,
the essence of the centers, you see? Now, Antariksha –
a essência dos centros, entendem? Agora, Antariksha,
you’ll be surprised that you are the essence of all the Antariksha,
vocês ficarão surpresos ao ver que vocês são a essência de toda Antariksha,
your centers are. Yes.
seus centros são. Sim.
Pujari [recites Pranayama prayer]: “Pranavasya Parabrahma rishi
Pranavasya Parabrahma rishi.
Paramatma Devata, Devi Gayatri chandah. Pranayame viniyogah.”
Paramatma Devata, Devi Gayatri Chandah. Pranayame viniyogah.
Shri Mataji: You do it only with the one nose? Yogi: Both noses. (Not audible)
- Você faz isso apenas com uma narina? - Ambas as narinas.
Shri Mataji: Both the noses. Prana: Prana is right side.
Ambas as narinas. Prana, Prana é o canal direito.
Prana shakti is right side, Mana shakti is left side.
Prana shakti é o canal direito, Mana shakti é o canal esquerdo.
So Prana shakti you are exciting
Então vocês estão estimulando o Prana shakti,
because this prana is the one which spreads in the body,
porque este prana é aquele se espalha no corpo,
gives you the balance, which takes in and gives out.
dá-lhes o equilíbrio, que absorve e dá.
Pujari: Now we have the Gayatri mantra.
Agora nós temos o mantra Gayatri.
Aum bhū, Om bhuvah,
Aum bhū, Om bhuvah,
Aum swah, Aum mah,
Aum swah, Aum mah,
Aum janah, Aum tapah, Aum satyam,
Aum janah, Aum tapah, Aum satyam,
Aum tat-Savitru-varenyam, bhargo devasya dhī-mahi
Aum tat-Savitru-varenyam, bhargo devasya dhī-mahi
Dhiyo-yo’nah prachodayāt Aum āpo jyotiras’omṛutam
Dhiyo-yo’nah prachodayāt Aum āpo jyotiras’omṛutam
Brahma bhūr-bhuvah swar’om
Brahma bhūr-bhuvah swar’om
Pujari e yogi: Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Pujari: Om Sriman Maha-Ganadhipataye namah,
Om Sriman Maha-Ganadhipataye namah,
Ishta devata-bhyo namah, kula-devata-bhyo namah,
Ishta devata-bhyo namah, kula-devata-bhyo namah,
grama-devata-bhyo namah. Shri Mataji: These are all pertaining to you.
grama-devata-bhyo namah.
Kula Devata is your dynasty, from where you come. There is a god who looks after that.
Kula Devata é a sua dinastia, de onde vocês vêm. Há um deus que cuida disso.
Then Grama Devata, of this village. There is a god who looks after this.
Depois Grama Devata, deste vilarejo. Há um deus que cuida disso.
Is all for you, pertaining to you. Then -
É tudo para vocês, pertencente a vocês.
Kula Devata? Pujari: Ishta Devata. Shri Mataji: Ishta, the One -
Kula Devata? Ishta Devata. Ishta, o Único,
your Ishta Devata is Me.
o Ishta Devata de vocês sou Eu.
Ishta means to whom we worship.
"Ishta" significa "a quem veneramos".
Pujari: Then: Sthana-devata-bhyo namah.
Sthana-devata-bhyo namah.
Shri Mataji: The god, the god that resides in this area.
O Deus, o Deus que reside nesta área.
Means the Divine part that it resides
Significa a parte Divina que
Pujari: Vastu-devata-bhyo namah.
Vastu-devata-bhyo namah.
Shri Mataji: The one – I don’t know if they do vastu here, but in every house in India
Aquele – Eu não sei se eles fazem vastu aqui, mas em todas as casas na Índia,
they put a kind of a vastu, means they put certain things
eles colocam uma espécie de vastu, significa que eles colocam certas coisas...
inside the foundation to protect the house.
dentro da fundação para proteger a casa.
Pujari: Mata pitrubhyam namah.
Mata pitrubhyam namah.
Shri Mataji: And your mother and father they are to be worshipped –
E a mãe e o pai de vocês, eles devem ser venerados,
they are to be saluted because you are part of them.
eles devem ser saudados, porque você é parte deles.
Pujari: Shri Lakshmi-Narayanabhyam namah.
Shri Lakshmi-Narayanabhyam namah.
Sarvebhyo devebhyo namoh namah. Sarvebhyo…
Sarvebhyo devebhyo namoh namah. Sarvebyo…
Shri Mataji: Lakshmi Narayan is, why… again see, Lakshmi Narayan.
Lakshmi Narayan é, por que... vejam, novamente, Lakshmi Narayan.
More insistence on Lakshmi Narayan, again, because of the Sushumna, again.
Mais insistência em Lakshmi Narayan, de novo, por causa do Sushumna, novamente.
The Void. Lakshmi Narayana. Sarva devobhyo Gurubhyo…
O vazio. Lakshmi Narayana. Sarva devobhyo Gurubhyo…
Pujari: Ah. Sarva gurubhyo Namah.
Sarva gurubhyo Namah.
Shri Mataji: All for your ascent, you see?
Tudo para a ascensão de vocês, entendem?
Pujari: Sarvebhyo-brahmanebhyo namah. Shri Mataji: All those who are
Sarvebhyo-brahmanebhyo namah.
All has to do with the ascent, see? How clear-cut it is.
Tudo tem a ver com a ascensão, entendem? Como isso é claro.
Pujari: Now the twelve names of Lord Ganesha.
Agora os 12 nomes do Senhor Ganesha.
Shri Mataji: Now. The twelve names of Ganesha because Ganesha must be
Agora, os 12 nomes de Ganesha, porque Ganesha deve ser…
awakened within you to begin with first, you see,
despertado primeiro dentro de vocês, antes de mais nada.
He must be first of all, and then open the source of Ganesha. Let’s have it.
Ele deve ser antes de tudo e depois abrir a fonte do Ganesha. Vamos fazer isso.
Pujari: Nirvighnamastu, Sumukhasch Ekdantascha,
Nirvighnamastu, Sumukhasch Ekdantascha,
Kapilo Gajakarnakah, Lambodarascha, Vikato, Vignanasho Ganadhipah
Kapilo Gajakarnakah, Lambodarascha, Vikato, Vignanasho Ganadhipah
Dhumra-ketur-Ganadhyaksho, Bala-chandro Gajananah
Dhumra-ketur-Ganadhyaksho, Bala-chandro Gajananah
Dvadash-aitani Namani, yah patet shrunu-yad-api
Dvadash-aitani Namani, yah patet shrunu-yad-api
vidya-rambhe vivahe-cha, praveshe nirgame tata
vidya-rambhe vivahe-cha, praveshe nirgame tata
sangrame sankate-chaiva, vignas tasya na jayate.
sangrame sankate-chaiva, vignas tasya na jayate.
Then all the mantras of the various Devas and Devis.
Depois todos os mantras dos vários Devas e Devis.
Shukl-ambara-dharam devam, shashi-varnam chatur-bhujam
Shukl-ambara-dharam devam, shashi-varnam chatur-bhujam
prasanna-vadanam dhyayet, sarva vignopa-shantaye.
prasanna-vadanam dhyayet, sarva vignopa-shantaye.
Sarva-mangala mangalye, Shive sarva-arta sadhike
Sarva-mangala mangalye, Shive sarva-arta sadhike
sharanye tryambake Gauri, Narayani namostute.
sharanye tryambake Gauri, Narayani namostute.
Sarvada sarva karyeshu, nasti tesham amangalam
Sarvada sarva karyeshu, nasti tesham amangalam
yesham hridisto bhagavan, mangalayatanam harih.
yesham hridisto bhagavan, mangalayatanam harih.
Tadeva lagnam sudinam tadeva, tara-balam chandra-balam tadeva
Tadeva lagnam sudinam tadeva, tara-balam chandra-balam tadeva
vidya balam daiva-balam tadeva, lakshmi-pateh tenghri yugam smarami.
vidya balam daiva-balam tadeva, lakshmi-pateh tenghri yugam smarami.
Labhas-tesham jayastesham kutastesham parajayah… Shri Mataji: Tesham.
Labhas-tesham jayastesham kutastesham parajayah. Tesham.
Labhas-tesham, to Them. Labhas-tesham.
Labhas-tesham, para Eles. Labhas-tesham.
Pujari: Yesham indivara shyame hridayaste janardanah.
Yesham indivara shyame hridayaste janardanah.
Shri Mataji: All - all about Shri Krishna. All about Shri Vishnu.
Tudo, tudo sobre Shri Krishna. Tudo sobre Shri Vishnu.
Pujari: Vinayakam, Gurum bhanum, Brahma-Vishnu-Maheshwaram
Vinayakam, Gurum bhanum, Brahma-Vishnu-Maheshwaram
Saraswatim pranamyadau sarva karyarta siddhaye.
Saraswatim pranamyadau sarva karyarta siddhaye.
Abhipa-sitartha siddhyartham pujito yah surah suraih
Abhipa-sitartha siddhyartham pujito yah surah suraih
sarva-vighna haras tasmai Ganadhi pataye namah.
sarva-vighna haras tasmai Ganadhi pataye namah.
Shri Mataji: Oh, Shri Ganesha’s. Pujari: Yes.
- Mantras de Shri Ganesha. - Sim.
(More mantras)
[Mais mantras]
Now we say where this puja is being - all, the time and… Shri Mataji: Yes.
- Agora dizemos onde este puja está sendo... -  Sim.
Pujari: Srimad bhagavato mahapurushasya vishnurajnaya pravartamanasya,
Srimad bhagavato mahapurushasya vishnurajnaya pravartamanasya,
adya brahmano-dvitiya parardhe vishnupade, sri svetavaraha kalpe,
adya brahmano-dvitiya parardhe vishnupade, sri svetavaraha kalpe,
vaivasvata manvantare - Krita Yuge -
vaivasvata manvantare - Krita Yuge -
England varshe - Europe kande - Cheltenham deshe.
Inglaterra varshe – Europa kande - Cheltenham deshe.
Shri Mataji: Ne - now why was what… Pujari: Why was what - Manvantare, Mother.
- Agora por que foi o que... - Por que foi o quê - Manvantare, Mãe.
Shri Mataji: Accha (hindi: yes). Pujari: Krita Yuge.
- Accha (Sim). - Krita Yuge.
Shri Mataji: Hm, Kruta Yuge… (hindi).
Krita Yuga.
It’s Kruta Yuge, this is time when you have to do something.
É Krita Yuga, esta é a época em que você tem de fazer alguma coisa.
Something will actualize, something will work out. This is Kruta Yuga.
Alguma coisa se concretizará, alguma coisa dará certo. Esta é a Krita Yuga.
Pujari: Thames uttara tire,
Thames uttara tire,
varshaa grishme, shraavana mase,
varshaa grishme, shraavana mase,
shukla pakshe, navami thatau…
shukla pakshe, navami thatau…
(Mantras continue)
(Mantras continuam)
[In the meantime Shri Mataji says: “Yes” to a child while
[Enquanto isso Shri Mataji diz: "Sim" para uma criança enquanto...
teaching her to keep her hands open.]
a está ensinando a manter as mãos abertas.]
Mataji Nirmala Devi priityartam - Sarva devi deva…
Mataji Nirmala Devi priityartam - Sarva devi deva…
Pujari e gli yogi: … Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
… Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Pujari: (continues with mantras).
(Mantras continuam)
Shri Mataji: Shoda Shopachaar. Shoda see, is sixteen.
Shoda Shopachaar. Shoda, é dezesseis.
Pujari: Yes. Shoda Shopachaar. Shri Mataji: Hm. Yes. See,
- Sim. Shoda Shopaar. - Sim.
whatever I have got, my knowledge, whatever we have got,
"Tudo que eu obtive, meu conhecimento, tudo que obtivemos,"
our knowledge, you see, and whatever things we have got,
"nosso conhecimento e seja quais forem as coisas que obtivemos,"
whatever we have got, means whatever we’ve got with us,
"tudo que obtivemos, significa tudo que temos conosco,"
we worship You, oh Mother.
"nós Te adoramos, ó Mãe."
With our sixteen ways of worship we do to You.
"Com nossas 16 formas de veneração, nós fazemos a Ti."
[Pujari continues with mantras]
(Mantras continuam)
Pujari: Now we start Ganesha Puja.
Agora começamos o Ganesha Puja.
Shri Mataji: All right. [Hindi].
Tudo bem.
[To the children] Please sit down comfortably, all right?
Por favor, sentem-se confortavelmente, tudo bem?
All of you should sit nicely.
Todos vocês devem sentar-se tranquilamente.
(Hindi)
(Hindi)
All right. Come along, all the children. [Sanskrit mantras]
Tudo bem. Venham, todas as crianças.
Wakra tunda mahakaya suryakoti sammaprabha
Wakra tunda mahakaya suryakoti sammaprabha
nirvighnam kuru me deva sarva karyeshu sarvada.
nirvighnam kuru me deva sarva karyeshu sarvada.
[More mantras for Ganesha]
[Mantras a Ganesha]
Shri Mataji: (Hindi)
(Hindi)
Wash My Feet.
Lavem Meus Pés.
Pujari: Om Bhur Bhuvah Swaha
Om Bhur Bhuvah Swaha
Shri Mahaganapatayé Namah Asanathe Akshatam Samarpayami.
Shri Mahaganapatayé Namah Asanathe Akshatam Samarpayami.
Om Bhur Bhuvah Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah Padyam Samarpayami.
Om Bhur Bhuvah Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah Padyam Samarpayami.
Namah Arghyam Samarpayami.
Namah Arghyam Samarpayami.
Om Bhur Bhuvah Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah…
Om Bhur Bhuvah Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah…
Shri Mataji: …Too much. …You do it later, you and Kalpana - (She corrects Herself)
Demais. Façam isso depois, você e Kalpana,
Aradhna, alright? Just wait here. Just wash it, wash it. …
Aradna, certo? Apenas espere aqui. Basta lavá-lo, lave-o.
Pujari: Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah
Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah
Snanam Samarpayami. [More mantras to Shri Mahaganapati are recited]
Snanam Samarpayami. [Mais mantras para Shri Mahaganapati são recitados]
Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah
Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah
Yajnopavitam Samarpayami. [More mantras to Mahaganapati]
Yajnopavitam Samarpayami. [Mais mantras para Mahaganapati]
Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah
Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah
[More mantras to Shri Mahaganapati are recited]
[Mais mantras para Shri Mahaganapati são recitados]
Om Bhur Bhuvah Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah
Om Bhur Bhuvah Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah
Alankarathe Akshatam Samarpayami.
Alankarathe Akshatam Samarpayami.
[Mantras continue]
[Mantras continuam]
Shri Mataji: …Aradhna [hindi]. Now let them do it, come along. Now… [hindi].
Aradhna. Agora, deixe-os fazer isso, venha. Agora.
Pujari: This is Shri Ganesha Atharva Sheersham.
Este é o Shri Ganesha Atharva Sheersham.
Shri Mataji: … That’s little [unclear]…
Isso é um pouco (…)
Pujari and the yogis: Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Mataji: Better…(hindi)… she’ll be better.
Melhor, ela ficará melhor.
[Pujari aside: “Finished the Ganesha Puja”]
Terminou o Ganesha Puja
Shri Mataji: Now, Gavin? Gavin: …finished with the Ganesha Puja.
- Agora, Gavin? - Terminamos o Ganesha Puja.
Shri Mataji: Hm? (Hindi) Pujari: Ganesha Puja… Shri Mataji: Hm?
Ganesha Puja.
Pujari: Finished the Ganesha Puja. Shri Mataji: Kya? (Hindi meaning what?)
- Terminou o Ganesha Puja. - O quê?
Pujari: Ganesha Puja is finished now. Shri Mataji: Finished now.
- Ganesha Puja terminou agora. - Terminou agora.
[Hindi conversation. Pujari: “Take two mantras”…
Recitemos dois mantras.
conversation in Hindi continues].
[Hindi]
Pujari: Take this water? Shri Mataji: Take it to wipe My feet.
- Levamos esta água? - Leve-a para limpar Meus Pés.
This water can be – [Pujari resumes mantras in Sanskrit]
Esta água pode ser…
better to put it on the Sahastrara of everyone. Specially the children.
Melhor colocá-la no Sahastrara de todos. Especialmente das crianças.
(Hindi)
[Hindi]
Shri Mataji: Now let them do it. Aradhna? …
Agora deixe-os fazer isso. Aradhna? …
[Pujari speaks probably in Hindi or Sanskrit.
[Hindi]
Shri Mataji replies and then in English: … or puja we will do.
(…) ou faremos o puja.
There’s nothing beyond, eh?
Não há nada além, hã?
Pujari: It is the worship of the picture as a representation of the universe,
É a veneração da imagem como uma representação do Universo…
which is present in front in the form of Shri Mataji.
que está presente na frente na forma de Shri Mataji.
[Then mantras in Sanskrit follow]
[Mantras]
Now the mantra of the earth, to stabilize our puja.
Agora o mantra da Terra para estabilizar nosso puja.
[long mantra to Pruthvi]
[Mantra para Pruthvi]
Now we are asking all the horrible things to go away, the bhuts and …
Agora nós estamos pedindo que todas as coisas horríveis vão embora, os bhoots e…
[Mantras in Sanskrit follow].
[Mantras].
Now we perform six things to purify our body,
Agora nós fazemos seis coisas para purificar nosso corpo,
we touch six parts of our body.
tocamos seis partes do nosso corpo.
Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Hridayaya Namah.
Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Hridayaya Namah.
Shri Mataji: First is heart, is important.
Primeiro é o coração, é importante.
Pujari: Next, the head. Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Shirsay Swaha.
Em seguida, a cabeça. Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Shirsay Swaha.
Next the back of your head, yes. Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Shikayay Vashak.
Em seguida, a parte de trás de sua cabeça. Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Shikayay Vashak.
Om – next to form a protection around us.
OM – o próximo para formar uma proteção ao nosso redor.
Shri Mataji: Vashak is like this, you see: Va Shak. Is a bandhan.
Vashak, é assim, veja, Vashak. É um bandhan.
Pujari: So, Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Shikayay Vashak.
Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Shikayay Vashak.
Then kavacha, Mataji… Shri Mataji: Kavach. Is a bandhan, yes.
- Depois o kavach, Shri Mataji. - Kavach. É um bandhan, sim.
Like this you can do it. Pujari: Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Kavachaya Swah.
- Você pode fazer assim. - Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Kavachaya Swah.
Pujari: Next the eyes, and the Agnya chakra. Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Nitrayaya Vashak.
Em seguida, os olhos e o Agnya Chakra. Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Nitrayaya Vashak.
Pujari: Next we put a bandhan. Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Astraya Phat.
Em seguida, fazemos um bandhan. Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Astraya Phat.
(Pujari aside: “…bandhan”) Shri Mataji: Do like this.
Façam assim.
Astra. Astra means the weapon.
Astra. Astra significa a arma.
[Pujari recites more Sanskrit mantras]
[Mantras]
Pujari: Now we invoke all the rivers. Gange cha yamune chaiva godavari
Agora invocamos todos os rios. Gange cha yamune chaiva godavari
sarasvati narmade sindhu kaveri jale'smin sannidhim kuru.
Sarasvati narmade sindhu kaveri jale'smin sannidhim kuru.
Now we salute the pitcher: kalashaya namah
Agora saudamos o vaso, kalashaya namah
[Sanskrit invocation follows].
[Sânscrito].
Now we worship the conch.
Agora veneramos a concha.
Next the bell.
Em seguida, o sino.
Shri Mataji: What is it? Pujari: Gantha.
- O que é? - Gantha.
This signifies the arrival of all the Devas and the departure of all the rakshasas.
Isso significa a chegada de todos os Devas e a partida de todos os rakshasas.
Next prayer to the lamp. [Mantras are recited]
Próxima oração para a lamparina.
Now the main puja, puja begins.
Agora o puja principal, o puja começa.
[Sanskrit mantras – then prayer to Vishnu:]
[Mantras]
Pujari: Now the mantras of the Goddess.
Agora os mantras da Deusa.
Namo Devyai Mahaa-Devyai Shivaayai Satatam Namah
Namo Devyai Mahaa-Devyai Shivaayai Satatam Namah
Namah Prakrtyai Bhadraayai Niyataah Prannataah Sma Taam.
Namah Prakrtyai Bhadraayai Niyataah Prannataah Sma Taam.
(mantra continues).
[Mantras]
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Avahanam Samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Avahanam Samarpayami.
Shri Mataji: Now the Avahana.
Agora o Avahana.
After awakening yourself, awakening all your channels,
Depois de despertar a si mesmo, despertando todos os seus canais,
now the Avahana is the calling, now you are inviting your Mother.
agora o Avahana é o chamado, agora você está convidando sua Mãe.
This is the nimantranam, this is the way you are inviting.
Este é o nimantranam, esta é a maneira que você está convidando.
[Shri Mataji calls one child to wash Her Feet] [Hindi].
[Hindi].
Pujari: (continues with mantras)
[Mantras]
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Asanathe Akshatam Samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Asanathe Akshatam Samarpayami.
(Continues with mantras)
[Mantras]
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Padyam Samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Padyam Samarpayami.
Padyam is the washing of the Feet of the Divine Mother.
Padyam é a lavagem dos Pés da Mãe Divina.
(Continues with mantras)
[Mantras]
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Arghyam Samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Arghyam Samarpayami.
Shri Mataji: Now it is very interesting, in Sanskrit language,
Agora, é muito interessante, em Sânscrito,
when you are using the water
quando você está usando a água…
to wash the Feet of the Goddess, then it’s called as Padyam.
para lavar os Pés da Deusa, então é chamado de Padyam.
When you are giving water for Mother to drink, it’s Arghyam.
Quando você está dando água para a Mãe beber, é Arghyam.
The word changes, you see.
A palavra muda.
Once it is for the Goddess, or for Gods, then the word is different.
Quando é para a Deusa ou para os Deuses, então a palavra é diferente.
For other people it is just water – they call it nira, jalam, anything.
Para outras pessoas, é apenas água, eles chamam de nira, jalam, qualquer coisa.
But for the Goddess it is padyam. Arghyam. Asanam. Pujari: Udaka also.
Mas para a Deusa. é padyam. Arghyam. Asanam.
Shri Mataji: Eh? Pujari: Udaka. Shri Mataji: Udaka, Udaka also.
Udaka, Udaka também. Derramar a água. A água que é derramada é chamada de Udak.
No other language has this. Pujari: Yes. Shri Mataji: No language –
Nenhuma outra língua tem isso. Nenhuma língua,
only except in English I think they call God “Thou”,
exceto apenas em inglês, Eu acho, eles chamam Deus de "Vós",
perhaps, maybe. Pujari: That is the limit. Shri Mataji: Eh?
- talvez. - Esse é o limite.
Pujari: That is the limit. Shri Mataji: That’s the limit. No more!
- Esse é o limite. Não mais.
For God if we call Thou You should be satisfied!
Para Deus, se chamamos "Vós", vocês devem ficar satisfeitos.
Yes, good. [Pujari continues with mantras.
Sim, bom.
Pujari: Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Acchamanayam Samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Acchamanayam Samarpayami.
Shri Mataji: Acchamanayam: whatever used, for… Pujari: Sipping.
Acchamanayam, tudo que for for usado…
Shri Mataji: Sipping, you see. Acchaman is sipping.
em goles, Acchaman é "em goles".
Of the Mother, is called as Acchamani.
Da Mãe, é chamado de Acchamani.
[Pujari recites names of Indian rivers in Sanskrit]
[Nomes dos rios indianos em Sânscrito]
Shri Mataji: All these rivers I bring to Your Feet to give You bath.
"Todos esses rios eu trago aos Teus Pés para banhar-Te."
Pujari: Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Snamayam Samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Snamayam Samarpayami.
Gavin: See, we are near the sources of two great rivers of this country here.
Nós estamos perto das nascentes de dois grandes rios deste país aqui.
Shri Mataji: What is that? Gavin: The Thames and Severn both start very close to here.
- Quais são? - O Thames e o Severn começam muito perto daqui.
Shri Mataji: Here? It’s Thames and…? Gavin: Severn. Yogi: Severn doesn’t start here.
- Aqui? É o Tamisa e...? - Severn não começa aqui.
Gavin, No, but there’s a tributary for it just… Yes.
Não, mas há um afluente para ele apenas... Sim.
Shri Mataji: Is it? Thames starts from here? Yogi: But the most (?)
- O Tamisa começa a partir daqui? - Mas a mais (…)
famous of all the springs that come out of the earth is Cheltenham, Mother.
famosa de todas as fontes que surgem da terra é Cheltenham, Mãe.
Yogis: Spa. Shri Mataji: Spa: ah!
- Spa. - Spa, ah!
Pujari: Now we offer ghee to Shri Mataji.
Agora oferecemos ghee para Shri Mataji.
Should we take another for You?
Devemos pegar outro para Senhora?
Shri Mataji: Ghee is to be offered.
O Ghee deve ser oferecido.
You see, if you want to use the Feet water this time then do it,
Se vocês quiserem usar a água dos pés desta vez, então façam isso,
it’s good, all right, start. Better do it, it’s good.
é bom, tudo bem, comecem. Melhor fazer isso, é bom.
Pujari: (recites Sanskrit mantras)
[Mantras]
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Ghruta snanam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Ghruta snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Nextly come milk.
Em seguida vem o leite.
Shri Mataji: Shuddhodaka, now water has to be poured out.
Shuddhodaka, agora a água deve ser derramada.
Pujari: Pure – not just – pure water.
Pura, não apenas isso, água pura.
Shri Mataji: But Shuddhodaka - is all right, pure water.
Mas Shuddhodaka - tudo bem, água pura.
Shuddhodaka - not even water it is, it is the water that is to be pured - poured,
Shuddhodaka, nem mesmo água, é a água que deve ser purificada, derramada,
is Shuddhodaka; and Shuddha is the pure.
é Shuddhodaka; e Shuddha é o puro.
Pujari: (Mantras)
[Mantras]
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Paya snanam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Paya snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Next we offer curd to Shri Mataji. Shri Mataji: Little hot – more hot water.
Em seguida, oferecemos coalhada para Shri Mataji.
Pujari: (Mantras)
[Mantras]
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah dadhi snanam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah dadhi snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Next, honey. Now we offer honey to Shri Mataji.
Em seguida, mel. Agora oferecemos mel a Shri Mataji.
(Mantras)
[Mantras]
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah madhu snanam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah madhu snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Shri Mataji: Milk has to be more. More milk.
Tem de ser mais, mais leite.
It’s all right, you can pour more milk now. In out of proportion it is.
Tudo bem, você pode colocar mais leite agora. Está fora de proporção.
Let’s keep heated milk, it is better, it doesn’t matter.
Vamos manter o leite aquecido, é melhor, não importa.
It should all go away when you put the sugar.
Tudo deve desaparecer quando você colocar o açúcar.
Pujari: Next we offer sugar to Shri Mataji.
Em seguida, oferecemos açúcar a Shri Mataji.
Has been pured from the sugarcane.
Foi refinado da cana-de-açúcar.
(Sanskrit mantras)
[Mantras]
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah sharkara snanam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah sharkara snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Shri Mataji: Now rub it on My Feet (the sugar – ed.). Would be better.
Agora esfregue nos Meus Pés. Seria melhor.
Then the fingers you see, just - it’s still there, quite a lot.
Depois os dedos, apenas - ainda estão lá, bastante.
The chakras are. (Somebody aside: “Shiny!”)
São os chacras.
Pujari: Next we offer to Shri Mataji three auspicious things
Em seguida, oferecemos a Shri Mataji três coisas auspiciosas…
mixed in water: camphor, sandalwood paste and perfume.
misturadas em água: cânfora, pasta de sândalo e perfume.
(Sanskrit mantras follow)
[Mantras]
Shri Mataji: Now on the Feet. Just pour it.
Agora nos Pés. Apenas despeje.
Now pour the water.
Agora despeje a água.
Too much. Yes, there. (Indistinct).
Muita. Sim ali.
Pujari: Now we are supposed to offer Shri Mataji sindhur,
Agora devemos oferecer a Shri Mataji sindhur,
tulasi leaves and turmeric powder.
folhas de tulasi e açafrão em pó.
Shri Mataji: Tulsi, tulsi leaves, first. That’s all, then I’ll remove My Feet.
Tulsi, folhas de tulsi, primeiro. Só isso, depois retirarei Meus Pés.
Offer tulsi leaves. Have you got tulasi here?
Ofereça folhas de tulsi. Você tem tulasi aqui?
Basil. You’ll get it later. All right? Good.
Manjericão. Você conseguirá mais tarde. Tudo bem? Bom.
(Sanskrit mantras for offering of tulsi)
[Mantras]
Now just wipe My Feet, take this out and I’ll put them on the ground,
Agora apenas limpe Meus Pés, tire isso e Eu os colocarei no chão,
now you can put…
agora pode colocar...
Pujari: Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah bhupam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah bhupam samarpayami.
Shri Mataji: Now spread something here down below,
Agora espalhe algo aqui embaixo,
put here something else, dry this.
coloque aqui alguma outra coisa, seque isto.
Yes. Just the sindhur and this thing, these things you put on My Feet.
Sim. Apenas o sindhur e esta coisa, estas coisas, coloque em Meus Pés.
And must – you must put keshar, keshar you haven’t got.
E você deve colocar keshar, keshar você não tem.
I should have brought keshar.
Eu deveria ter trazido Keshar.
lLet’s try, saffron. Pujari: Because here in this country we can get it.
- Vamos tentar, açafrão. - Porque aqui neste país podemos conseguir.
Shri Mataji: Saffron you get quite a lot. Pujari: It’s quite easy.
- Açafrão você consegue bastante. - É bem fácil.
Shri Mataji: Very easy. Saffron is very good. Now.
Muito fácil. O açafrão é muito bom. Agora.
Pujari: We should take some photographs. Shri Mataji: Hm?
Nós devemos tirar algumas fotos?
Shri Mataji: Yes.
- Nós devemos tirar algumas fotos? - Sim.
Before… even Sahaja yogis…
Antes... até mesmo dos Sahaja Yogis...
Pujari: Mataji Shri Nirmala…
Mataji Shri Nirmala…
Shri Mataji: First put the dried one, have you got the dried?
Primeiro coloque o que está seco, você tem o seco?
Just akshata, mix it up in that, it’s all right.
Apenas akshata, misture com isso, tudo bem.
Just this, you see.
Apenas isso.
Little bit, yes. That’s all.
Pouco, sim. Só isso.
Now what else? Pujari: Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah
- Agora o que mais? - Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah
Bhupam Samarpayami Deepam darshayami.
Bhupam Samarpayami Deepam darshayami.
(Mantras continue)
[Mantras]
Shri Mataji: Now just put that one, yes. Do like this, Gavin.
Agora é só colocar aquele, sim. Faça assim, Gavin.
Yes. All right.
Sim. Tudo bem.
Pujari: Now to the five forms of Pranayami.
Agora para as cinco formas de Pranayami.
Shri Mataji (to Gavin): Now the karpura (camphor) little bit.
Agora o karpura (cânfora), um pouco.
Rub it up.
Esfregue.
Now the offering whatever I have to eat –
Agora a oferenda de tudo que tenho para comer.
something you have…(indistinct words) sweet or chana will do.
Vocês têm algo (...) doce ou farão chana?
Chana, chana is absolutely best, I love chana.
Chana, chana é absolutamente o melhor, Eu adoro chana.
This is Naivedhyam, you see, just (indistinct).
Isto é Naivedhyam, apenas (…).
Only the Brahmins eat everything, the Gods don’t eat anything.
Só os brâmanes comem tudo, os Deuses não comem nada.
That’s all right.
Tudo bem.
Pujari: Om Shri Pranaya swaha. Shri Mataji: Chana.
- Om Shri Pranaya swaha. - Chana.
Pujari: Om Shri Apanaya Swaha. Om Shri Bhyanaya Swaha.
Om Shri Apanaya Swaha. Om Shri Bhyanaya Swaha.
Om Shri Uddhanaya swaha. Om Shri Samanaya swaha.
Om Shri Uddhanaya swaha. Om Shri Samanaya swaha.
Om Shri Brahmané swaha. Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Om Shri Brahmané swaha. Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Shri Mataji: Use this thing. Just use this. This one. Warren: Should use this.
- Use esta coisa. Apenas use isto. Isto. - Deveria usar isto.
Pujari: (Mantras)
[Mantras]
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Mantra Pushpam Samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Mantra Pushpam Samarpayami.
Namaskaranami
Namaskaranami
(mantras follow).
[Mantras]
Now we come to the main puja.
Agora chegamos ao puja principal.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Abhisheka Snanam Samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Abhisheka Snanam Samarpayami.
Shri Mataji: I know.
Eu sei.
(Pujari starts recitation of mantras)
[Mantras]
This is actually when You are in a statue.
Isso, na verdade, é quando a pessoa está em uma estátua.
SYou can only do all this when You are in a statue.
Você só pode fazer tudo isso quando a pessoa estiver em uma estátua.
Pujari: (Mantras)
[Mantras]
Pujari: Now we can - sari, Mataji, vastraya.
Agora podemos - o sari, Mataji, vastaraya.
Shri Mataji: Vastra. [Pujari aside: “You got some sari?”] Sari…(hindi).
- Vastra. - Vocês têm algum sari?
What sari? What’s that?
Que sari? O que é isto?
No, no, no. Sari’s out of question.
Não, não, não. O sari está fora de questão.
Pujari: Which vastran, then?
Qual vastran, então?
Shri Mataji: Which one they opened within now - anything.
Qual deles eles abriram agora, qualquer coisa.
No, now - any vastran you can use that – do... [Yogi softly: “We could try”]
Não, agora, qualquer vastaran, você pode usar este.
Good.
Bom.
Pujari: (Recitation of mantras)
[Mantras]
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Vastran Samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Vastran Samarpayami.
Aum - Sandal.
Aum – Sandália.
(Mantras for offering of sandal)
[Mantras para oferenda da sandália]
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah chandanam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah chandanam samarpayami.
Then some more akshata, Mataji. (Mantras)
Então um pouco mais de akshata, Mataji.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Akshatam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Akshatam samarpayami.
Now. (More mantras)
Agora. [Mantras].
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah haridram samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah haridram samarpayami.
Make sindhur offers (kumkum).
Faça oferendas de sindhur (kumkum).
(Mantras)
[Mantras]
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah kumkumam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah kumkumam samarpayami.
Pujari: (Mantra)
[Mantras]
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah kajalam samarpayami. (Offer of kajal)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah kajalam samarpayami. (Oferernda de kajal)
(Mantra)
[Mantras]
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah
kantha sutram samarpayami. (Offer of sutra for the neck)
kantha sutram samarpayami. (Oferenda do sutra para o pescoço)
[Shri Mataji speaks in Hindi]
[Hindi]
(Mantra)
[Mantras]
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah
kankanam samarpayami. (Offer of bangles)
kankanam samarpayami. (Oferenda de pulseiras)
(More mantras follow)
[Mantras]
[Shri Mataji speaks in Hindi]
[Hindi]
Pujari: Shall we do the Sahastranama (…) - Lalita Sahastranama?
Vamos fazer o Sahastranama (…), Lalita Sahastranama?
Shri Mataji: [Hindi conversation with pujari.
[Hindi]
“Puja… Havan… Havana…
"Puja… Havan… Havana…
Devi Mahatmya…”. Pujari: “Devi Mahatmyam”]
- Devi Mahatmya…" - Devi Mahatmyam.
So the beginning of it - and then say it, read it in English, would be better.
Então, o começo disso - e depois recitá-lo, lê-lo em inglês, seria melhor.
[Pujari starts reading in Sanskrit]
[Sânscrito]
If you read it in English would be better. Pujari: Read it in English.
- Se você ler em inglês seria melhor. - Leia em inglês.
Shri Mataji: Hm, then whatever is in English is the story.
Assim, seja o que for que esteja em inglês é a história.
It’s better that they understand.
É melhor que eles entendam.
(Hindi) All right, stand up and read it.
[Hindi] Tudo bem, levante-se e leia.
Pujari: This is the great hymn to the Goddess when She had killed Mahishasura,
Este é o grande hino à Deusa quando Ela matou Mahishasura,
whom as we all know is back again in Bangalore.
quem, como todos sabemos, está de volta em Bangalore.
“To that Ambika who is worthy of worship by all the devas and sages,
Para aquele Ambika que é digno de veneração por todos os Devas e sábios,
and who pervades this world by Her power,
e que permeia este mundo pelo poder Dela,
and who is the embodiment of the entire power
e que é a personificação de todo o poder,
of all the hosts of Devas, we bow in devotion.
de todas as hostes de Devas, nos curvamos em devoção.
May She grant us auspicious things.
Que Ela nos conceda coisas auspiciosas.
May Chandika whose incomparable greatness and power,
Que Chandika, cuja grandeza e poder incomparáveis,
Bhagavan Vishnu, Brahma and Hara are unable to describe,
Bhagavan Vishnu, Brahma e Hara são incapazes de descrever,
bestow Her mind on protecting the entire world,
conceder Sua mente em proteger o mundo inteiro...
and on destroying the fear of evil.
e em destruir o medo do mal.
Oh Devi, we bow before You. Who are Yourself good fortune
Oh Devi, nós nos curvamos diante de Ti. Que é Tu mesma a boa sorte…
in the dwellings of the virtuous, and ill-fortune in those of the vicious,
nas moradas dos virtuosos e a má sorte nas moradas dos vicios,
intelligence in the hearts of the learned, faith in the hearts of the good,
a inteligência no coração dos eruditos, fé no coração dos bons,
and modesty in the hearts of the high-born.
e modéstia nos corações dos nobres.
May You protect the Universe!
Que Tu protejas o Universo!
Oh Devi, how can we describe Your inconceivable form,
Ó Devi, como podemos descrever Tua forma inconcebível...
or Your abundant, surpassing valour that destroys the asuras,
ou Teu valor abundante e inigualável que destrói os asuras,
or Your wonderful feats displayed in battles
ou Teus feitos maravilhosos exibidos em batalhas…
amongst all the hosts of Gods, asuras and others?
entre todas as hostes de Deuses, asuras e outros?
You are the origin of all the three worlds, though You are possessed of the three gunas,
Tu és a origem de todos os três mundos, embora Tu possuas as três gunas,
You are not known to have any of their attendant qualities.
Tu não és conhecida por ter qualquer uma de suas qualidades relacionadas.
You are incomprehensible even to Vishnu, Shiva and others.
Tu és incompreensível até mesmo para Vishnu, Shiva e outros.
You are the resort of all. The entire world is composed
Tu és o refúgio de todos. O mundo inteiro é composto…
of an infinitesimal portion of Yourself.
de uma porção infinitesimal de Seu Si.
You are verily the Supreme Primordial Prakruti. Untransformed.
Tu és verdadeiramente o Prakruti Primordial Supremo. Não transformado.
Oh Devi, You are swaha, at whose utterance
Ó Devi, Tu és swaha, em cuja elocução…
the whole assemblage of Gods obtain satisfaction in all the sacrifices.
toda a assembleia de Deuses obtém satisfação em todos os sacrifícios.
You are the swadha…” Shri Mataji: Same.
- Tu és o swadha… - O mesmo.
Now, these are the mantras of the swaha: Bhuh is pruthvi, is Ganesha Tattwa.
Agora, estes são os mantras do swaha: Bhuh é pruthvi, é o Ganesha Tattwa.
Then you said swah. Pujari: Yes. Om Bhuh Bhuvah Swah.
- Então você disse swah. - Sim. Om Bhuh Bhuvah Swah.
Shri Mataji: Swah is the satisfaction.
Swah é a satisfação.
Bhuvah is the Antariksha, the whole universe.
Bhuvah é o Antariksha, o Universo inteiro.
Pujari: You are the swadha which gives satisfaction to the manes…
Tu és o swadha que dá satisfação aos manes…
Shri Mataji: Swa-dha: swa is your self,
"Swa-dha", "swa" é você mesmo,
dha means you have sustained yourself with your Self.
"dha" significa "Tu sustentastes Ti mesma com o Teu Si".
Swadha is the quality of the Nabhi chakra.
Swadha é a qualidade do Nabhi Chakra.
Pujari: “Therefore you are chanted by people.
Portanto, Tu és cantada pelas pessoas.
Oh Devi, You are Bhagavati, the Supreme Vidya,
Ó Devi, Tu és Bhagavati, o Supremo Vidya,
which is the cause of liberation and great inconceivable penances.
que é a causa da libertação e das grandes penitências inconcebíveis.
You are the Supreme Knowledge, are cultivated by sages who desire liberation,
Tu és o Conhecimento Supremo, que é cultivado por sábios que desejam a liberação,
whose senses are well restrained and who are devoted to reality
cujos sentidos são bem contidos e que são devotados à realidade…
and have shed all the blemishes.
e tirou todas as manchas.
You are the soul of Shabda-Brahma, You are the repository of the very pure…”
Tu és a alma de Shabda-Brahma, Tu és o repositório do muito puro…
Shri Mataji: Logos, logos you call? - Shabda-Brahma. OM.
Logos, você chama de logos? O Shabda-Brahma. OM.
“You are the Soul of that”. Pujari: OM. All the Vedas come out of it (unclear).
- "Tu és a alma disso". - OM. Todos os Vedas vêm disso (...).
Shri Mataji: Everything is created out of that OM. Shabda-Brahma is OM,
Tudo é criado a partir desse OM. Shabda-Brahma é OM,
and out of that all this Brahma – means Brahmanda - is created, out of OM.
e a partir disso, todo esse Brahma, significa Brahmanda, é criado a partir do OM.
Pujari: Shabda-Brahma. Shri Mataji: All the scriptures.
- Shabda-Brahma. - Todas as escrituras.
Pujari: “You are the repository of the very pure Rik and Yajus hymns
Tu és o repositório dos hinos muito puros de Rik e Yajus…
and of the Sama hymns, the recital of those words is beautiful with the Udgitha.
e dos hinos Sama, a recitação dessas palavras é bela com o Udgitha.
You are Bhagavati, embodying the three Vedas.
Tu és Bhagavati, incorporando os três Vedas.
And You are the sustenance whereby life is maintained.
E Tu és o sustento pelo qual a vida é mantida.
You are the Supreme Destroyer of the pain of all the worlds.
Tu és a Suprema Destruidora da dor de todos os mundos.
Oh Devi, You are the intellect, by which
Ó Devi, Tu és o intelecto, pelo qual…
the essence of all scriptures is comprehended. You are Durga,
a essência de todas as escrituras é compreendida. Tu és Durga,
the boat that takes men across the difficult ocean of worldly existence
o barco que leva os homens através do oceano difícil da existência mundana,
devoid of attachments. You are Shri
desprovida de apegos. Tu és Shri,
who has invariably taken Her abode in the heart of Vishnu.
que invariavelmente tomou Tua morada no coração de Vishnu.
You are indeed Gauri who has established Herself with Shiva.
Tu és realmente Gauri, que se estabeleceu com Shiva.
Gently smiling, pure, resembling the full moon’s orb,
Delicadamente sorridente, pura, semelhante ao orbe da lua cheia,
beautiful like the splendor of excellent gold was Your face.
bela como o esplendor do ouro esplêndido era o Teu rosto.
Yet it was very strange that, being swayed by anger, Mahishasura could not bear it.
No entanto, era muito estranho que, sendo influenciado pela raiva,
Far strange it is that after seeing Your wrathful face, O Devi,
Muito estranho é que depois de ver Teu rosto, ó Devi,
terrible with its frowns and red in hue like the rising moon,
terrível com Teus olhares irados e vermelhos em matiz como a lua nascente,
that Mahishasura did not immediately give up his life!
de modo Mahishasura desistiu imediatamente da vida dele.
For, who can live after beholding the enraged Destroyer?
Pois quem pode viver depois de contemplar a Destruidora enfurecida?
O Devi, be propitious. You are Supreme.
Ó Devi, seja propícia. Tu és Suprema.
If enraged, you forthwith destroy the (asura) families
Se enfurecida, Tu destróis imediatamente as famílias (de asuras)...
for the welfare of the world. This was known
para o bem-estar do mundo. Isso foi conhecido no momento exato…
the very moment the extensive forces of Mahishasura were brought to their end.
em que as extensas forças de Mahishasura foram levadas ao seu fim.
You are always bounteous, to those fortunate ones with whom You are well pleased,
Tu és sempre generosa para aqueles afortunados com quem Tu estais satisfeita,
are indeed the object of esteem in the country,
Tu és de fato o objeto de estima no país,
theirs are riches, theirs are glories, and their acts of righteousness perish not;
deles são as riquezas, deles são as glórias e os atos deles de justiça não perecem;
they are indeed blessed and possessed of devoted children, servants and wives.
eles são realmente abençoados e possuem filhos devotados, servos e esposas.
By Your Grace, O Devi, the blessed individual does daily
Por Tua Graça, ó Devi, o indivíduo abençoado faz diariamente…
all righteous deeds with utmost care and thereby attains to heaven.
todas as ações corretas com o máximo cuidado e através disso alcança o céu.
Are You not, therefore, O Devi, the bestower of reward in all the three worlds?
Tu não és, portanto, ó Devi, A que concede recompensa em todos os três mundos?
When called to mind in a difficult position, You remove fear from every person.
Quando lembrada em uma situação difícil, Tu removes o medo de cada pessoa.
When called to mind by those in happiness, You bestow a mind still more pious.
Quando lembrada pelos que estão felizes, Tu concedes uma mente ainda mais piedosa.
Which Goddess but You, O Dispeller of poverty, pain and fear,
Que Deusa senão Tu, ó Dissipadora da pobreza, da dor e do medo,
has an ever sympathetic heart for helping everybody?
tem um coração sempre solidário para ajudar a todos?
The world attains happiness by the killing of these foes;
O mundo alcança a felicidade da aniquilação desses inimigos;
and though these asuras have committed sins enough
e embora esses asuras tenham cometido pecados o suficiente…
to keep them long in hell,
para mantê-los por muito tempo no inferno,
let them reach heaven by meeting death eventually at battle with You.
deixe-os chegar ao céu encontrando a morte eventualmente em batalha Contigo.
Thinking thus, it is that You, O Devi, certainly destroy our enemies.
Pensando assim, é que Tu, ó Devi, certamente destrói nossos inimigos.
Don’t You reduce to ashes all asuras by mere sight?
Tu não reduzes a cinzas todos os asuras pela simples visão?
But You direct Your weapons against them so that even the wicked ones,
Mas Tu diriges Tuas armas contra eles de modo que até os ímpios,
purified by the missiles, may attain higher worlds." Shri Mataji: Yes.
- purificados pelos projéteis, talvez alcancem mundos superiores. - Sim.
Pujari: “Such is Your most kindly intention towards them”.
Tamanha é a Tua mais gentil intenção para com eles.
Shri Mataji: This one you read again.
Leia este de novo.
Pujari: “Don’t You reduce to ashes all asuras by mere sight?
Tu não reduzes a cinzas todos os asuras pela simples visão?
But You direct Your weapons against them so that even the wicked ones,
Mas Tu direcionas Tuas armas contra eles de modo que até os ímpios,
purified by the missiles, may attain the higher worlds”.
purificados pelos projéteis, talvez alcancem mundos mais elevados.
Shri Mataji: May attain. May. Pujari: May.
Talvez alcancem, talvez.
“That is Your most kindly intention towards them.”
Essa é a Tua intenção mais gentil em relação a eles.
Shri Mataji: Not promised.
Não foi prometido.
Pujari: “If the eyes of the asuras had not been blinded by the terrible flashes
Se os olhos dos asuras não tivessem sido cegados pelos terríveis clarões…
of the mass of light issuing from Your sword
da massa de luz que sai de Tua espada...
or by the copious luster of Your spear point,
ou pelo brilho abundante de Tua ponta de lança,
it is because they saw also Your face resembling the moon,
é porque eles viram também o Teu rosto semelhante à lua,
giving out cool rays.
emitindo raios frescos.
O Devi, Your nature is to subdue the conduct of the wicked;
Ó Devi, Tua natureza é subjugar a conduta dos ímpios;
this is Your peerless beauty inconceivable by others;
esta é Tua beleza inigualável inconcebível por outros;
Your power destroys those who have robbed the Devas of their prowess,
Teu poder destrói aqueles que roubaram os Devas das proezas deles,
and You have thus manifested Your compassion even towards the enemies.
e assim manifestastes Tua compaixão até para com os inimigos.
What is Your prowess to be compared to? Where can one find this beauty (of Yours)
Com o que Tua proeza deve ser comparada? Onde se pode encontrar essa beleza…
most charming, yet striking fear in enemies?
mais encantadora, mas infligindo medo nos inimigos?
Compassion in heart and relentlessness in battle are seen, O Devi,
Compaixão no coração e implacabilidade na batalha são vistas, ó Devi,
O Bestower of boons, only in You in all the three worlds!
Ó Doadora de bênçãos, somente em Ti, em todos os três mundos.
Through the destruction of the enemies all the three worlds have been saved by You.
Através da destruição dos inimigos, todos os três mundos foram salvos por Ti.
Having killed them in the battlefront, You have led even those hosts of enemies
Depois de matá-los na frente de batalha, Tu levastes até mesmo aquelas hostes de...
upwards, and You have dispelled our fear of the frenzied enemies of the Devas.
inimigos para cima, e Tu dissipastes nosso medo dos inimigos alucinados dos Devas.
Salutations to You.
Saudações a Ti.
Oh Devi, protect us with Your spear. O Ambika, protect us with Your sword,
Ó Devi, protege-nos com Tua lança. Ó Ambika, protege-nos com Tua espada,
protect us by the sound of Your bell and by the sound of Your bow-string.
protege-nos pelo som do Teu sino e pelo som da corda do Teu arco.
O Chandika, guard us in the east, in the west, in the north and in the south
Ó Chandika, proteje-nos no leste, no oeste, no norte e no sul,
by the waving of Your spear, O Ishwari!
pelo movimento de Tua lança, ó Ishwari!
Protect us and the earth with those lovely forms of Yours,
Protege-nos e à Terra com essas Tuas belas formas,
moving about in the three worlds, as also with Your terrible forms.
movendo-se nos três mundos, assim como também com Tuas formas terríveis.
O Ambika, protect us on every side with Your sword, spear and club
Ó Ambika, protege-nos de todos os lados com Tua espada, lança e clava…
and whatever other weapons Your soft hand has touched. Amen.
e quaisquer outras armas que Tua mão suave tenha tocado. Amém.
Pujari and the yogis: Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Mataji: Very well. All right. Just vibrations are too much.
Muito bem. Tudo bem. Somente vibrações, são demais.
(Hindi) Havan? Eh? Pujari: ...Aarti...
- Havan? - ...Aarti...
Shri Mataji: Aarti. [Hindi conversation with pujari]
Aarti. [Hindi]
Pujari: Let us sing the Aarti to Shri Mataji now.
Vamos cantar o Aarti para Shri Mataji agora.
Shri Mataji: Don’t play those… which one were you playing yesterday?
Não toquem esses... qual era o que vocês estavam tocando ontem?
Which bell were you playing yesterday?
Qual sino vocês tocaram ontem?
Yesterday which one was played?
Ontem qual foi tocado?
Warren: Which one did you use yesterday? It was bad sound.
Qual você usou ontem? Era um som ruim.
Yogi: These small brasses. Shri Mataji: These? You know, something else was there.
- Estes pequenos latões. - Estes? Algo mais estava lá.
Yogi: Somebody had some different… Shri Mataji: Hm? What’s that?
- Alguém tinha algo diferente... - O que é isto?
These you used yesterday? These are all right.
Estes vocês usaram ontem? Estes estão bem.
Yesterday something else was here. Yogi: They’re metal, Mother, they’re not brass.
- Ontem algo mais estava aqui. - Eles são de metal, Mãe, não são de latão.
Shri Mataji: Let Me see. These are from where? Ah, this is good.
Deixe-Me ver. Esses são de onde? Este é bom.
These are from India? Gavin: Some present from India, yes.
- Estes são da Índia? - Alguns presentes da Índia, sim.
They were given to the sahaja yogis in Bombay, I think. Shri Mataji: Who gave?
- Eles foram dados aos Sahaja Yogis em Mumbaim, eu acho. - Quem deu?
Gavin: Somebody in India, I don’t know… Shri Mataji: No, it’s not correct,
- Alguém na Índia, eu não sei. - Não, não está correto,
this is not all right. That’s all right, that’s all right.
Este não está bom. Tudo bem, tudo bem.
And this you need not play. Only that will do.
E você não precisa tocar este. Só este servirá.
For that you have a very big one, which goes with the complete, you see,
Para isso, você tem um bem grande, que vai com o completo,
because the movement –
porque o movimento -
next time they are going to present you with that bell, big bell,
da próxima vez, eles os presentearão com este sino, sino grande,
and the antah gharial (?).
e o antah gharial (…).
Such vibrations, I tell you.
Muitas vibrações, Eu lhes digo.
Yogi: Sarva Devi Deva Maha Moksha Pradayini Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi ki! Yogis: Jai!
Sarva Devi Deva Maha Moksha Pradayini Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi ki! Yogis: Jai!
Om twameva Sakshat Shri Mahalakshmi
Om twameva Sakshat Shri Mahalakshmi
Mahasaraswati Mahakali
Mahasaraswati Mahakali
Trigunatmika Kundalini Sakshat
Trigunatmika Kundalini Sakshat
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat Shri Bhagavati Sakshat
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat Shri Bhagavati Sakshat
Shri Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Om twameva Sakshat Shri Kalki Sakshat
Om twameva Sakshat Shri Kalki Sakshat
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat Shri Bhagavati Sakshat
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat Shri Bhagavati Sakshat
Shri Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Om twameva Sakshat Shri Kalki Sakshat
Om twameva Sakshat Shri Kalki Sakshat
Shri Sahastrara Swamini Moksha Pradayini Mataji
Shri Sahastrara Swamini Moksha Pradayini Mataji
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Pujari: Bolo Shri Parameshwari Mata Shri Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi ki!
Bolo Shri Parameshwari Mata Shri Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi ki!
Yogis: Jai!
Jai!
Yogi: Bolo Shri Mahadevi Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi ki! Yogis: Jai!
Bolo Shri Mahadevi Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi ki! Yogis: Jai!
Yogi 2: Nirmala Shakti Mataji
Nirmala Shakti Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi ki! Yogis: Jai!
Shri Mataji: Today I bless you specially that you’ll meet all My bhaktas,
Hoje Eu os abençoo especialmente para que vocês encontrem todos os Meus bhaktas,
and Sahaja Yoga will grow very fast, all over the world.
e a Sahaja Yoga crescerá muito rápido, no mundo inteiro.
I also bless you, those people who will try to attack you,
Eu também os abençoo, essas pessoas que tentarão atacá-los...
will become sahaja yogis.
se tornarão Sahaja Yogis.
The highest of all, I bless you with the power of cleansing yourself,
O mais elevado de tudo, Eu os abençoo com o poder de se purificar,
and cleansing others with your love, with your devotion, with your dedication.
e purificar os outros com seu amor, com sua devoção, com sua dedicação.
May Adi Shakti bless you then.
Que a Adi Shakti os abençoe então.
Yogi: Jai Mataji!
Jai Mataji!
Gavin: Mataji Nirmala Devi ki! Yogis: Jai!
Mataji Nirmala Devi ki! Jai!
Shri Mataji: May God bless you.
Que Deus os abençoe.
Gavin: Mother, whatever mistakes we’ve made… Shri Mataji: How much time do we have
Mãe, quaisquer que sejam os erros que cometemos...
for the lunch? What time did you have lunch?
Quanto tempo temos para o almoço? A que horas vocês almoçaram?
Yogi: Yesterday it was about quarter to one, Mother.
Ontem foi por volta de 12h45, Mãe.
Shri Mataji: Will they do it at one o’clock, if you tell them? So we can finish?
Eles comerão às 13h se você lhes falar? Então podemos terminar?
Yogi: It’s normally one o’clock. One o’ clock. Shri Mataji: See?
- Normalmente é às 13h. 13h. - Entendem?
Please ask them to keep it one. All right. Or one fifteen,
Por favor, peça-lhes para manter às 13h. Tudo bem. Ou 13h15,
one fifteen would be better. Or one o’ clock. All right.
13h15 seria melhor. Ou 13h. Tudo bem.
Yogi: Mother, he told me quarter to one… Shri Mataji: Hm?
Mãe, ele me disse 12h45...
Yogi: …before the puja. Shri Mataji: What’s it?
- (…)antes do puja. - O que é isso?
Yogi: The warden told me quarter to one for the lunch.
O diretor me disse 12h45 para o almoço.
Warren: Quarter to one. The warden told him a quarter to one,
12h45. O diretor disse a ele 12h45,
before starting the puja.
antes de iniciar o puja.
Shri Mataji: Just request him … Warren: We could change.
- Apenas peça a ele... - Nós poderíamos mudar.
Yogi: Let’s just change it, just change it to one o’clock. Yogi 2: One o’ clock, yes.
- Vamos apenas mudar, mude para 13h. - 13h, sim.
Shri Mataji: You see, you say that I went and told they -
Diga que Eu fui e disse a eles,
because it is one o’clock always, so better to have it at one. Let’s go down.
porque é sempre às 13h, então é melhor às 13h. Vamos descer.
There should be no objection because, for having earlier, you know, people.
Não deve haver objeção porque, por ser mais cedo, as pessoas.…
Yogi: No, no, no. Shri Mataji: (Hindi)
- Não, não, não. -  [Hindi].
Is there any arrangement already? Yogi: No. For havan? (Inaudible)
- Já existe algum preparativo? - Não. Para o havan?
You know, we don’t actually - in India you don’t get (indistinct).
Na verdade não temos - na Índia você não consegue (…).
What is this? Is rather particular one.
O que é isto? É bastante particular.
Yogi: I think it’s a metal alloy. Shri Mataji: Eh?
- Acho que é uma liga de metal. - Hã?
Yogi: I think it’s a metal alloy… metal alloy - mixture of metals.
Acho que é uma liga de metal, liga de metal, mistura de metais.
Shri Mataji: Ah, metal… (indistinct words, sentence ends with ‘maryada’ or ‘maryadas’).
Ah, metal…